[Music]
this board is a continuation of the
statement now there are two cases
depending on the sign of the
Overflow if the
Overflow is
negative then
generically generically means unless
you're really unlucky unless you're in
exceptional strange situation the K and
L don't intersect you can just fit them
without any
overlap if in contrast the Overflow is
positive or
zero those of us who learned mathematics
in the English speaking world will call
this positive or zero because for us
positive means strictly positive those
of us who don't mathematics in the
French speaking civilization we call
that just positive and if there's no
equality we say we call that strictly
positive I'll combine these terms so if
the Overflow is
positive of zero then
generically the intersection is nonempty
in other words there is an intersection
and the dimension of that non-empty
intersection if you like here the point
at which two lines meet or the line
along which two planes meet and so on is
exactly equal to the Overflow
notice that this can happen the second
case can happen when the Overflow is
zero that means that two sub manifolds
meet in a Zero Dimensional intersection
but Zero Dimensional intersection does
not mean no intersection it means
meeting in points points have zero
Dimensions yeah it does not mean oh
that's interesting something happened
there
okay now
this
is you might say Elementary linear
algebra and that's it for the proof well
this is the kind of thing that
professors will often do they say oh you
have learned the linear algebra and you
know everything about linear algebra and
the fact of the matter is we learned
linear algebra a few years ago and and
we don't quite remember what was linear
algebra and then they say oh it's
Elementary line albra and then go it's
not kind so I'd like to give you a
picture in order to understand this make
it more
intuitive however the picture that I
shall draw is not a picture but we shall
call it a
picture let's imagine that you want to
put the k dimensional
space
Subspace how do you represent the K
dimensional Subspace well how many
parameters do you need to represent a k
dimensional Subspace well K parameters
right let's say that you have
a an N di the ambient Dimension is n so
K dimensional Subspace looks like
this you have some parameters K of them
which can take arbitrary values yeah you
go in K independent directions but the
remaining directions will all be
zero does that make
sense think of for example
R3 let's say that we want to have
something onedimensional inside the
ukian space R3 how do you do that well
you can represent it by
this x can be anything this represents
when X takes all values the x-
axis what Y and Z directions are
constraint to be zero boom boom and
that's one dimension if you want a two
dimensional object in R3 you can do this
X and Y are three parameters they can
take anything so this when you vary X
and Y will move all over the horizontal
plane but the vertical coordinate is
constraint be zero so that's two
dimensional okay and that's exactly the
same thing but in higher Dimensions okay
so that's the k dial case how about the
L dimensional case well
again they M components and let's try to
make the overlap as small as
possible that means that you see there
are lots of nonzero numbers here and
zero numbers here so I want to put all
the nonzero numbers at the bottom and
make zero at the top so we shall put the
L
dimensional some manifold
and parameterize them by
putting it in this form so there L
entries which are completely free so
they can be take arbit numbers and the
rest are
zero okay so that's a k Dimension that's
L Dimension inside a common ambient
space that has Dimension n now question
do they
overlap the answer is they overlap if
and only if this comes down far and this
comes up far if there are not many of
them not many of them they don't
overlap okay but you see what's the
overlap that's k and l and m you can
figure out over that and because some of
us are feeling the
temperature if you have General K let's
say that K is quite large and L is quite
large how much overlap do you get in the
middle man
you have you have K the whole density is
M and you start fitting K SS from above
El SS from below and they sometimes
overlap what's the overlap in terms of k
and l and
m yeah
no let's go over up let's do it in
3D two Dimensions X and Y and Zer and
then maybe Y and Z and Zer so this is
also two and two inside three what's the
overlap you overlap in the middle right
overlap Dimension is one that's because
there are two here two here but the
ambient Dimension is
three you start overlapping so what's
the overlap dimension in the
middle yeah yeah so but in terms of k
and l and m how much overlap is
there K plus L minus M exactly and that
guess what is the definition of the
Overflow so that's the overlap Dimension
that you get and this
is as I say the picture of this
theorem do you understand what the
picture is it's very strange I didn't
draw a picture but in some sense you can
see that you are thinking geometrically
when we do this in terms of a simple
example that you kind of visual you are
not of course visualizing because K
might might be 200 and M might be 500
higher dimensional spaces but we still
feel that we understand that's one way
to do geometry
okay any questions and it's getting very
hot so well I thought in Madagascar it
was hotter than this but
it's of course it's also after lunch
next week we'll be doing this before
lunch when everyone's hungry and quite
nervous so it would go better
okay now so
far we had a static picture in other
words some manifolds manifolds and so on
they were not moving they just stay
there and we contemplated them we just
watched them at rest let's start moving
once sub
manifold inside a
manifold and try to go around an
obstacle run into an obstacle and so on
let's move some
manifolds as before we'll start with
some illustrative examples and then
we'll be able to guess what the general
result
[Music]
is again in
R2 imagine that we have a line R2 and a
point on one side of the line and this
point which you might think of as say
Tadashi and this is the river wants to
go from one side to the other side of
the
river well at some point tashi's feet
will get
wet it's sometimes known as the
intermediate value
the
Okay so
in R2 so two dimensional
space our point which has Dimension
zero moving from one side of a
line to another to the other side and
please don't worry too much about what
we mean by side
one
side
to the other
side over a
line which has Dimension
one must make a
Crossing
okay the situation you realize is a
little different from the static
situation before because you see this is
dimension zero this is dimension one
dimension is two there's a lot of
ambient Dimension and nonetheless they
must
intercept why do they have to intercept
0 + 1 is less than two overflow seems to
be negative and nonetheless they must
intersect
next if you do the same thing in
R3 a point moving from one side to the
other
side of a line
Tashi starts going there but then he
sees that the river is coming and he
wants to avoid the intersecting the
river what does he do where is the stick
there
huh exactly he comes like this and he
goes I could jump because there was a
third dimension into which to jump I
could Escape into this extra Di
[Music]
it can
avoid the
crossing okay that's
interesting
let's think about this
in R3
then a line which has Dimension
One
moving from one side to the other side
of the line
from one
side to the other
side of a line another
line which also has Dimension
One what happens in order to do
this would you kindly hold this like
that and then don't let it go so that's
one line we are stay we are inside a
three dimensional space and that's
another line and please imagine that
this line goes up and down infinitely
when I come
across I have to make a cross right I
cannot avoid this Crossing I might try
to go but I might try to
go you might be thinking what about this
ah but remember this line is infinitely
long so it goes so there is no way to
avoid the
[Music]
[Applause]
crossing
however in R4 four dimensional space
[Applause]
it can avoid a
Crossing hey can you hold it again how
do we avoid the Crossing in R4 well this
is the line infinite line and it comes
and then it's like Tadashi area when he
comes here he wants to jump into an
extra
Dimension it jumps and so this part
disappears from 3D just as excuse me
when I was jumping across the river I
disappeared from the two dimensional
plane I left the two dimensional plane
so if you just observing me in the two
dimensional plane it looks like like I
disappeared and then suddenly appeared
again
yeah wo so so it's the same thing I
deform myself into a higher
Dimension and then reappear
here and I can cross over it's perfectly
rigorous so in R4 you can avoid a
cross amazing
stuff so what is the general theorem and
this is
the main fact that underlies the
operation of
isotopy the dynamic picture of um
Crossing and not
crossing the
[Applause]
so imagine that you have two sub manles
k l inside
M and they're such that the Overflow the
Overflow which we Define I like to
remind you what it was Dimension K plus
Dimension L minus Dimension M that's the
Overflow now do you remember in the
static
case overflow had to be strictly
negative in order to avoiding
intersection in other words strictly
less than
zero but here in the dynamic case when
you move one thing past each other you
see that you need a little more
overflow
and so we'll start from zero and this
and zero so that you do get some
intersection so that excuse me so that
you um so that you don't get the
intersection initially so that the
theorem one by theorem one initially
they are not
Crossing now suppose that I start moving
then they might start Crossing you see
so K
moves just like those examples bear in
mind those examples please from one
side to the other side side of
L starts moving in that like that and we
really want
to avoid
Crossing tries
to step
aside or step around as we did when I I
jumped or as we disappeared into an
extra Dimension and came back okay step
us
around to
avoid the
crossing okay theorem or the result if
the Overflow we know that overflow is
negative but it overflow
is sufficiently negative that is
less than or equal to minus
one oh excuse me um is equal minus one
then it
fails excuse
me
so Crossing is
inevitable
happens whereas if the
Overflow is less than minus one
then it
succeeds that is crossing is
[Applause]
avoided that's the theory
as usual it's much better to draw a
picture and understand it in ter of of
of the picture indeed writing it like
this in words makes things look
complicated um in fact the way I
prepared this statement is I first drew
a picture and then looking at the
picture described it in words that's the
order in which I did it I didn't have
the statement and try to draw a picture
it's the other way
around so here's the
picture Z Zia okay so let's draw Zia
and
that two people
and they are having this sub manifold l
inside the manifold M and then Tashi is
trying
to cross
over so this is K and it's moving
forward okay and the question is is it
going
to Cross or not or can I avoid it
intersection
now here is the
idea as K
moves we thought the dimension of that
matter was dimension of K but in fact it
isn't when K moves imagine that K sweeps
out the whole screen whole whole
surface okay
that's the trajectory of K it's leaving
behind sort of a cloud smoke screen and
that has a lot of Dimension and the
question is whether L is going to
intersect that trajectory of of K so as
K moves it sweeps out do you know this
expression yeah do you know this
expression so when I move for example
something like this can you imagine the
surface that is Left Behind when I move
that's called the surface swept out by
this by this stick okay and if you have
a point it
moves what is swept out by this point is
a is a curve okay you sweep out because
sweeping is what you do when you have a
you know broom and so forth okay it
sweeps
out a surface
of Dimension what's
Dimension Dimension k +
okay so stepping
around as we call
it to avoid the
intersection would be successful
if there is enough ambient Dimension to
avoid intersection between this screen
this s out surface and
L if this
surface or let's call it sheet because
that's
probably
more suggested if sheet yeah
there's not
intercept L but what is the condition
for the avoiding
[Applause]
intersection
by which theorem is
this do I have it is that number
two yeah that's right by theor number
two
no the number one because it's we're
using Theory number two is what we are
proving number one is what we already
know sheet and L will have empty
intersection generically you can sort of
generically part it to El intersection
if the Overflow which is one plus
dimension of K that's the dimension of
the sheet yeah plus dimension
L minus dimension of M is negative
strictly
negative but what is this it is simply
equal to this number is Overflow it's 1
plus the
Overflow and you see that therefore it's
successful you can avoid a Crossing if
and only if the Overflow is strictly
less than minus
one that's the condition if it's equal
to minus one you're in the case where
the the this sheet and L intersect in
points in Zero Dimensional things that's
the
uh conclusion
okay I'll add one or two cories and then
that's
it okay have you heard of not
Theory huh have you not Theory first of
all not Theory doesn't mean
not
Theory it'sot Theory not Theory so
theory of
Nots things like that this is noted this
is not noted and so not Theory have you
heard of this this used to be quite
popular but maybe now it's not so
popular so I'm going to show you that no
theory is a very special subject and
it's not generally applicable first cor
is three
you know if you have something like that
without cutting you cannot unot it to
make
this
yeah I should have brought a string in
fact uh somebody was doing this last
night yeah you cannot unnote this to
make
this yeah you cannot because if you have
a string imagine that this is made of
string I cannot make it into this shape
inside
R3 I do you agree yeah you can see this
I really wish that I was wearing a shoe
with shoelaces does anybody have a
shoeless no
okay okay do you know what I'm talking
about what do you know what the shoelace
is it's the string that you
[Music]
have M can you lend me your Sho Sho this
in a moment
okay you have a oh that's but I can cut
it right because we have no no scissors
somewhere anyway in
aims thank you very much thank you I'll
return it and so thank you very much to
M for his support in the mathematical
Sciences yeah so this
is yeah a simple Loop but now let's take
something
else if we have something like that let
me tie a
not excuse
me yeah something like
this yeah I cannot
undo this note what am I doing here
anyway something like this yeah I cannot
undo this and make it just a
straight it's clear but I cannot undo
this in 3D
but that's because I cannot undo this
because we are in threedimensional space
in four dimensional space we
can we can sort of go to the four
dimensional
space it's it left and it will come back
in a moment it's in the four dimensional
space
now just one second it takes quite a
while to go to the four dimensional
space yeah yeah yeah but that's because
Egyptian women have special vision and
and it comes like this
so that's the statement it sounds crazy
but we shall see that it is
true so
every not made of
strings
yeah every string KN excuse
me made of a
curve yeah I'm going to discuss other
things so made of
curve can be
unoted
in RM for all
M from four dimensions and above that's
in 3D you cannot that's why we have all
those knes in 3D in our space but inti
dimensions they can all be unnoted and
the proof is very
easy you see suppose that you have two
parts of this string one part is like
this and then another part is like this
it's passing behind and suppose that by
some magic I
can make this part of the string come
across and appear on the other side
without
intersecting well if I can do that
operation I can unot
everything right so the question is can
I do this operation or not and we
can in this Dimension this
move is
possible without
Crossing
if by the theorem that we have just
proved theorem two
the Overflow which is 1 + one because
you have one dimension here one
dimension here and minus the ambient
Dimension m is strictly less than minus
one but this inequality says that m is
strictly greater than three that means m
is greater than or equal to
okay so
I
oops you in other words in four
dimensions and above all knots can be
unnoted there are no knots everything is
Trivial that's quite
interesting however another interesting
thing
is in
R2 if you go down too much in dimension
from this space to thing
on the other
hand in R2 so we had R4 and above but in
R2 a loop like
this might be a nice Loop but it could
be a loop like
this it might cross
itself now may I borrow this so if you
have a loop which is crossing
like like this on the
plane well your natural instinct is I
don't o what's this I don't like this
Crossing so I'm going to undo the
crossing by lifting one strand of the
loop from the other now they don't cross
any yeah but that and doing the crossing
can is possible because we have an extra
Dimension into which we can escape in R2
you may not be able to escape for
example this is is
stuck however you move however you this
Crossing Will Survive so in R2 a loop
like this may
have
generic uh self
intersections in other words
intersections that cannot be made to
Disappear by small preservations yeah
and that's by theorem one if you do the
calculation of the
Overflow so
it means that in R2 usually knots or
Loops have self intersections which we
don't like in our four and above all kns
are trivial so the only dimension in
which not theory is interesting is R3
there's no other
damage not Theory becomes completely
trivial in R4 and above and becomes too
ugly in R2 the only Dimension by not
Series in interesting is R3 so
that's not Theory it's a big subject so
you might like to look at that but is
interesting
only
in three dimension three okay that's
enough